If you’re anything like me,
you have lots of ambitious
plans for the future.
I’ve got a whole series of
new books I want to write,
thousands more
videos to script.
But guess what?
None of us may be able to do
any of the things we want to do
if we don't have our health.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we have part two
of our series on resveratrol
and we start with a study
that shows that resveratrol appears to
triple the rate of age-related brain shrinkage.
Does resveratrol help
with inflammation?
In humans, the evidence
of an anti-inflammatory effect
is sparse and conflicting.
About half of the studies show
a modest
anti-inflammatory effect,
but the other half
failed to find any.
The proof, however,
is in the pudding.
What about clinical effects
on inflammatory disease?
In rats and mice,
resveratrol can help
ameliorate the effects
of experimentally-induced
periodontitis,
the inflammatory gum disease.
However, it appears
to have no effect
on the progression
of chronic periodontitis
in human sufferers.
Resveratrol may help with
the inflammatory bowel disease
ulcerative colitis, though.
A pilot study
of 500 milligrams a day
of resveratrol for six weeks
resulted in significantly
decreased disease activity
and elevated quality of life
compared to placebo.
What about inflammatory
joint disease?
One pilot study
of 500 milligrams a day
of resveratrol
for knee osteoarthritis
found a decrease in pain
within a month,
but there was no control group;
so, the change can't
really be attributed
to starting the supplements.
However, a second pilot study,
a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial,
found that the same dose
taken as an "add on"
to an anti-inflammatory drug
significantly improved
pain and function
within a month
in mild-to-moderate
knee osteoarthritis sufferers,
more than adding a placebo.
The one clinical trial
of rheumatoid arthritis
had a control group,
but no placebo,
though there were
objective signs of improvement
in disease activity after
taking 1000 milligrams a day
for three months.
Resveratrol may also be
beneficial
to combat menopausal symptoms.
Resveratrol has
some estrogenic activity.
Although it doesn't appear
to help with hormonal migraines,
it does appear to help
with a couple symptoms of PCOS,
polycystic ovary syndrome.
RESHAW—Resveratrol
for Healthy Ageing in Women—
is the longest study of effects
of resveratrol supplementation
in postmenopausal women.
Those randomized
to 75 milligrams
of resveratrol twice a day
suffered significantly fewer
physical menopausal symptoms,
including aches and pains,
and a general improvement
in overall well-being
compared to placebo.
The RESHAW study also looked
at bone loss prevention.
Unfortunately,
though animal studies
show protective effects
on bone tissue,
a meta-analysis
of human studies
on resveratrol supplementation
to improve bone quality
found no significant effect
on bone health markers
or bone mineral density
of the spine, hip,
or overall skeleton.
A similar story was found
for cognitive effects.
Most studies on resveratrol
for brain function
in animal models
show positive outcomes,
but meta-analyses
of human studies show
no significant effect
on memory,
processing speed,
executive function,
or global
cognitive performance,
which led reviewers to suggest
that resveratrol may be
a "cognitive enhancer
for mice only."
Most human cognition studies
found no effect
or mixed results—higher
performance on some tasks,
but lower performance on others,
compared to placebo,
resulting in
a "lack of interpretable
cognitive effects."
Some have suggested
the discrepancy
between the animal models
and the clinical data
is that the rodents
were massively dosed,
up to a gram per kilogram
of body weight a day,
which would be
like giving people
an entire bottle
of high-dose resveratrol
supplements at once.
Or, ironically,
it could be the opposite,
where the doses researchers
gave people were too large.
A dose-response study
found that human
cerebral blood flow
was maximally boosted
by the lowest dose
of resveratrol tested,
seventy-five milligrams a day.
So, when the RESHAW study
was developed,
that was the dose they used,
given twice a day.
RESHAW was primarily designed
to test the effects
of resveratrol
on cognitive performance.
Interim analyses at 14 weeks
and a year looked promising,
leading the researchers
to conclude that their findings
"support the adoption
of resveratrol
as a low-cost,
effective intervention
to help counteract the age-
and menopause-related
accelerated cognitive decline
in our ageing population."
However, by the end
of the two-year study,
it's not clear
if the apparent benefit
in overall cognition
survives adjustment
for multiple comparisons,
meaning there were so many
cognitive outcomes tested
that the few treatment
differences
may well have arisen
through chance.
What about cognitive benefit
for those who really need it?
Observational studies
find wine drinkers
tend to get less dementia,
but it's hard to disentangle
the social, cognitive,
and personality factors
that accompany
a wine drinking habit.
So, researchers decided
to put resveratrol to the test
for Alzheimer's disease.
A randomized double-blind,
placebo-controlled pilot
out of Cornell in 2006
kicked things off with a bang.
Patients with mild-to-moderate
Alzheimer's disease
who were randomized
to a 5 milligram
resveratrol concoction
twice a day
ended up with significantly
better cognition
after three months
compared to placebo.
There was a greater
than expected deterioration
in the placebo group, though,
suggesting that this may
have just been a fluke,
especially since an attempt
to replicate the study
with the same dose for a year
failed to find any effects
of statistical significance.
Maybe the researchers just
didn't use a high enough dose?
More than a hundred patients
with mild to moderate
Alzheimer's
were randomized to placebo
or an escalating dose
of resveratrol
starting at a hundred times
the dose
of the previous study—
500 milligrams once a day
and ending at a 1000 milligrams
twice a day.
After a year,
there were no significant
improvements in cognition
or the performance of activities
of daily living
compared to placebo.
Instead, there was
a significant acceleration
of brain volume loss.
At the end of the study,
there was triple
the brain volume loss
(3 percent versus 1 percent)
in the resveratrol group.
And the only other randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial to date
found the same thing:
no significant
cognitive benefits
and the same tripling
of age-related brain shrinkage.
The authors tried to somehow
spin this as a positive,
like hey—maybe that's just
decreased brain swelling,
but as a team
of researchers wrote
in an understatement
of the year,
"It is difficult
to reconcile these effects
as potentially beneficial."
In our final story of the series,
we discover how
resveratrol supplements
may blunt some of the positive
effects of exercise training.
If you do have a condition
that might benefit from
resveratrol supplementation,
like diabetic foot ulcers,
or ulcerative colitis,
or menopausal pains,
and want to give resveratrol
a try,
are there any concerns,
aside from the cost,
which can exceed $10 a day?
Well, although a meta-analysis
of studies of resveratrol
found no overall effect
on LDL cholesterol levels,
a couple studies
found that resveratrol
sometimes increased LDL levels,
up to 25 percent over placebo.
As cardiovascular disease
is by far the leading killer
of diabetics,
as well as other conditions
for which you might take it,
if you do try resveratrol,
please make sure
to have your cholesterol
closely monitored.
The scientific literature
regarding resveratrol
and cardiovascular health
in general is said to be
"replete with conflicting
information and controversy."
There are no human studies
on cardiovascular disease
outcomes,
but an often-overlooked study
found that resveratrol caused
atherosclerosis in rabbits.
The study, entitled
"Resveratrol promotes
atherosclerosis
in hypercholesterolemic
rabbits,"
found that the hardening
of the arteries of bunnies
fed dietary cholesterol
was worsened by resveratrol.
But, negative or null findings
are often marginalized
by the resveratrol
research community;
so, you rarely hear about them.
Though there are
no long-term safety data,
450 milligrams a day
has been considered a safe dose,
at least in the short term,
for a 60 kilogram person
(that's like 130 pounds),
but supplementation
at higher doses
could be potentially toxic.
Daily doses of resveratrol
in excess of a gram
commonly cause mild to moderate
gastrointestinal symptoms,
such as nausea, diarrhea,
abdominal pain,
as well as "anal itchiness."
Unexpected renal toxicity
with cases
of severe kidney failure
were noted
in a five-gram-a-day study,
but this was in the context
of a cancer
that is particularly hard
on the kidneys.
Two studies, however, found
that so-called "safe" levels
of resveratrol
(at 150 to 250 milligrams a day)
may blunt
some of the positive effects
of exercise training.
In rodents, resveratrol
supplementation decreases
cardiovascular risk factors
and improves
cardiovascular function
and physical capacity.
But, when it was
put to the test in older men
(with an average age of 65),
the exact opposite was found.
Specifically,
combining resveratrol
with athletic training
abolished the reduction
in blood pressure, cholesterol,
and triglycerides
normally associated
with exercise,
had a more artery-constricting
effect than a dilating one,
and led to a significantly
lower increase
in aerobic fitness.
Rodents on resveratrol get
enhanced exercise performance,
but, in people,
the resveratrol induced
a 45 percent lower increase
in maximum aerobic capacity
compared with those
taking a sugar pill.
For all their working out,
the resveratrol
was undercutting their efforts.
An apparent impairment
in peak aerobic power
was also noted in young men
following high-intensity
interval training
on resveratrol
compared to placebo.
A recent review
overreacted to these data
by suggesting "foods
containing resveratrol
should not be consumed
during exercise,"
but to even reach
the lower dose of 150 milligrams
you'd have to eat
more than like
a hundred pounds
of grapes a day.
Though, I suppose
if you did manage to stuff
in a hundred pounds of grapes,
it might, indeed,
be a little impairing.
The exercise impairment
with resveratrol supplements
does make sense, though,
given its purported mechanism.
Sirtuin activation
by resveratrol
is thought to occur
via the activation
of the body's fuel gauge, AMPK,
by interfering
with energy production
in the mitochondria powerplants
in our cells.
Mouse cells react by increasing
mitochondria to compensate,
but human cells
apparently do not;
so, the energy-dimming effect
of resveratrol
may explain why the effects
of exercise are impaired.
What works in animals may not
necessarily work in people.
Thus, concluded one review,
the hype regarding resveratrol
may "turn out to be
nothing more
than a sleight-of-hand
marketing device
using peer-reviewed, published,
non-human research
as a cover."
Although some like Dr. Oz
have recommended resveratrol
as a life-extending
"miracle molecule,"
given that evidence-based
responses
are sparse-and-controversial
such "claims, innuendo,
and hyperbole"
are said to be "atrocious."
The fitness-blunting exercise
study of older adults
was supported in part
by a manufacturer
of resveratrol supplements.
To their credit,
the researchers responded
to an angry letter from
a supplement company consultant
that "it is our opinion
that we, as scientists,
have a responsibility
to report what we find
and not to twist our findings
to fit the commercial interests."
Unquote.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age” has
been out for about half a year now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.